Finding Aid for Warren W. Florer papers, 1877-1955
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Warren W. Florer papers 1877-1955
Florer, Warren Washburn, 1869-
1.5 linear feet and 1 oversize folder
851211 Aa 2; Ac
Professor of German at University of Michigan. Correspondence, articles, speeches and research notes.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Warren W. Florer (donor no. 1523 )
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Warren W. Florer was born May 17, 1869, in Loda, Ill., a son of William J. and Mary Ann Washburn Florer. He received his AB degree in 1890 and MA degree in 1893 from DePauw and his PhD degree in 1897 from Cornell. He also attended Leipzig University. Following graduation, he came to the University of Michigan as an instructor in German. He was appointed assistant professor in 1907 and held this position until his retirement from the University in 1918. For the remainder of his life, Florer was a researcher and historian, mainly in the study of German immigration to Michigan. He was author of a series of three volumes on "Early Michigan Settlements." In these volumes, he examined the settlement of Washtenaw County, Catholic settlement of Westphalia, the Lutherans of the Frankenmuth area, the German student revolution of 1848 in Detroit, and German missionary activities among the Indians. Florer also wrote several articles on the works of Martin Luther and in the field of education. He was a lecturer on the American Revolution and on the struggle for liberty in Germany from 1517 to contemporary times. He died April 16, 1958.
The Florer papers have been arranged into the following series: Correspondence; Personal; University of Michigan; Education and the Teaching of German; and Articles and research materials. Some of Florer's correspondents include James B. Angell, Wilber M. Brucker, Fred W. Green, Harry B. Hutchins, and Harry F. Kelly. Some of the other files of interest concern his interests in Louis Kossuth, Gustav Frenssen, Hermann Kiefer, and the Schilling family of Scio township, Washtenaw County, Michigan. There are also materials on early German settlers of Michigan, and the firing of members of the German Department of the University of Michigan during World War I.
Subjects:
Clinton (Mich.); Discrimination in employment--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Florer, Warren Washburn, 1869-; Frenssen, Gustav, 1863-1945; German Americans--Michigan.; Kiefer, Hermann, 1825-1911.; Kopp, Anton.; Kossuth, Lajos, 1802-1894.; Schilling family.; Scio (Mich.: Township); Sons of the American Revolution. Michigan Society. Washtenaw County Chapter No. 1.; Washtenaw County (Mich.); University of Michigan. Board of Regents.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Germanic Languages and Literatures.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; World War, 1914-1918--Education and the war.; World War, 1914-1918--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Visual Materials - Subjects
Florer, Warren Washburn, 1869-
Contributors:
Angell, James Burrill, 1829-1916.; Brucker, Wilber Marion, 1894-1968.; Green, Fred Warren, 1872-1936.; Hutchins, Harry B. (Harry Burns), 1847-1930.; Kelly, Harry F. (Harry Francis), 1895-1971.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Correspondence
  - 1877-1901 (Box 1)
  - 1902-1909 (Box 1)
  - 1910-1915 (Box 1)
  - 1916-1920 (Box 1)
  - 1930-1941 (Box 1)
- Personal
  - Education at the University of Leipzig (Box 1)
  - Washtenaw County chapter of the Sons of the American Revolution (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous clippings (Box 1)
  - Photographs (Box 1)
  - Photostats of newspaper clippings (Folder 1)
  - Collected German documents (Folder 1)
  - Certificate of appointment as instructor first lieutenant in the University's Reserve Officer Training Corps, 1918 (Folder 1)
- University of Michigan career, 1897-1918
  - Bismarck celebration at the University of Michigan (newspaper clippings concerning), 1914 (Box 1)
  - Anti-socialist speeches by Florer (newspaper clippings and correspondence concerning), 1912 (Box 1)
  - The German Department at the University of Michigan (particularly during World War I (Box 1)
- Education and the Teaching of German
  - Teaching of German in Michigan high schools (Box 1)
  - Surveys on the teaching of German in Michigan high schools, 1912-1915, 9 folders (Box 1)
  - Education in Lutheran schools (Box 1)
- Articles and research materials
  - Hessians in colonial America (Box 1)
  - Louis Kossuth's visit to Ohio, Michigan, Illinois and Indiana (Notes for an article on) (Box 1)
  - Ernst Peter Schilling family of Scio Township, Washtenaw County (Box 1)
  - Anton Kopp (early German settler of Clinton, Mich.) (Box 1)
    (missing)
  - The German Element in Michigan (manuscript) (Box 1)
  - Schiller
    - Speeches given about (Box 1)
    - Draft of paper on Schiller and the American Revolution (Box 1)
  - Hermann Suderman (Box 1)
  - Materials for article on classical writers (Box 1)
  - Rough drafts of articles on religious topics (Box 1)
  - Offenburg and Freiberg resolutions (Box 1)
  - Article on Art vs. Formalism (Box 1)
  - Notes on the Eschenburg manuscript (Box 1)
  - Notes for Use of German (Box 1)
  - Article on Goethe (Rough draft of) (Box 1)
  - Gustav Frenssen, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Hermann Kiefer, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Martin Luther
    - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
    - Materials concerning Martin Luther's translation of the Psalms, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Poem by Freiligrath and correspondence concerning its publication, 1950-1955 (Box 2)
  - Photostats acquired in research projects, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous Articles and Speeches, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous notes (Box 2)